Guide to the Stoothoff family collection ARC.150
Brooklyn Historical Society
Stoothoff family collection
1642-1826
Brooklyn Historical Society
Stoothoff, Elbert Elbertse
Stoothoff family
Stoothoff, Wilhelmus
ARC.150
2 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes and one oversize box
This collection contains 140 manuscript documents and other papers dating from the 1600s to 1826, relating to the Stoothoff family of Flatlands, Long Island, which is now part of Brooklyn, New York. Documents include deeds, bonds, wills, correspondence, accounts, and receipts. Many of the documents are in Dutch. An index of all documents and translations of all Dutch documents accompanies this collection.
Biographical / Historical
Captain Elbert Elbertse Stoothoff, or "Justice of the Peace" (who signed his name "Elbert Elbertsen"), is the common ancestor of the Stoothoff family in the Flatlands area of Brooklyn, New York. He was born in 1620,and emigrated from Nieukerken, in 1637, but was bound to serve Kilian Van Renseselaer for six years in his colony. Afterward, he settled in Flatlands, and was one of the nine men appointed by the Freeholders of the community from 1648 to 1650 to represent "Manhattans, Breukelen, Amersfoort, and Pavonia." His duties included the promotion of welfare of the country, and to assist in decision-making regarding matters submitted by the director of the council. Elbertsen served as a magistrate of the Flatlands from 1654 to 1673. Elbertsen married Aeltje Cornelis Cool in 1645, and was married a second time, after her death, in 1683 to Sara Roelofs. Gerrit Stoothoff was the only child of Elbert and Aeltje, and he married into the Nevius (sometimes spelled Neveyus) family in 1684. Peter and Wilhelmus Stoothoff, two of his six children, are among the primary correspondents in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains manuscript documents and papers pertaining to the Stoothoff family of Flatlands, Long Island (now part of Brooklyn, New York) from 1642 to 1826. Document types include deeds, bonds, correspondence, receipts, accounts and account books, and wills. Among the many items in this collection are detailed accounts of debits and credits of various everyday items for citizens of New Amersfoort (the Dutch name for Flatlands) in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, as well as Elbert Elbertsen Stoothoff's own personal accounts, his will, and various letters to him regarding the sale of land and business transactions. A detailed account book of the sale (or vendue) of the estate of Wilhelmus Stoothoff is located in this collection, documenting the prices for various items in his home including artwork, fabrics, and furniture. This collection also contains letters and bills of sale regarding the sale of enslaved persons in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection are arranged in the manner imposed by the donor. There are 116 folders (numbered 1-116), each folder containing between one and three documents. Placed before these 116 folders is an index to the documents and translations to those in Dutch; the numbers in the index correspond to the numbers on the folders. Two additional documents (1812 and 1826 deeds) relating to the family which were not part of the original accession have been placed at the end of the collection. These two items are not included in the collection's index.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Stoothoff family collection was purchased from the Bergen family in 1920 by the Colonial Daughters of the Seventeenth Century of Brooklyn, who later donated the collection to the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society) in 1922.
The index that accompanies this collection was most likely compiled by Josephine Frost; the translations were done by Frank L. Van Cleef.
Two additional deeds relating to the family were donated by Mrs. D. Fogarty in 1988. Mrs. Fogarty was the great-granddaughter of William Stoothoff.
Prenuptial agreements; Bonds |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Flatlands (New York, N.Y.); Indentures; Affidavits; Genealogy; Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); Account books |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Certificates; Deeds; Wills; Correspondence; New Netherland; Conover family; Gerritse family; Stoothoff, Wilhelmus; Stoothoff, Cornelius; Stoothoff, Peter; Stoothoff, Gerrit; Neveyus, Johannes; Nevius, Cornelius; Stoothoff, Elbert Elbertse; Couwenhoven family; Stoothoff family; Hubbard, Elias
- Index and Translations by Frank L. Van Cleef, undated; 4280 (Box 1, Folder data_value_missing_04b0393312f1f62647c2ef3aec3e7783)
- 1. Receipt, Roelofsz to E. Elbertsen's executor, 1695; 3705 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1. Receipt, J. Gerritsen Van Couwenhoven to E. Elbertsen, 1687; 3706 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 2. Antenuptial Agreement, E. Elbertsen and S. Roelofs, 1683; 3707 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 3. Receipted bill, Loockermans to E. Elbertsen, 1665; 3708 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 4. Account, E. Elbertsen to Gerritsen's heirs, 1663-1664; 3710 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 5. Contract to sell, Cornelissen to E. Elbertsen, 1684; 3711 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 6. Quit-claim, Willett and Van Dyckhuys to Stoothoff, 1695; 3712 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 7. Deed, W.G. Van Couwenhoven to E. Elbertsen, 1660; 3713 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 8. Agreement, W.G. Van Couwenhoven to E. Elbertsen, 1646; 3714 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  General
  One document contains agreement and four receipts for legacy.
- 8. Receipts for legacy, Martensen, et. al. to E. Elbertsen, 1660-1670; 3716 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 9. Account book, E. Elbertsen, 1676-1678; 3717 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 10. Deed, W.G. Van Couwenhoven to E. Elbertsen, 1659; 3718 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 11. Deed, M. Van Couwenhoven to E. Elbertsen, 1671; 3719 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 12. Bond, Schenck and Terhunen to E. Elbertsen's heirs, 1695-1696; 3720 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 13. Deed, Luyster to E. Elbertsen, 1687; 3721 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- 14. Deed, E. Elbertsen to G. Elbertsen, 1687; 3722 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 15. Deed, W. Gerritsen's executors to E. Elbertsen, 1666; 3723 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- 16. Conditions of Sale, H. Hoogland sale of property, 1772; 3724 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- 17. Sale of "negro," E. Hubbard to W. and P. Stoothoff, 1782; 3725 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- 18. Articles of agreement, P. Couwenhoven and E. Elbertsen, 1667; 3726 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- 19. Dates of marriage and birth dates of children, J. Stoothoff and C. Bogert, 1738-1780; 3727 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- 20. Affidavit, E. Elbertsen, 1642; 3728 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- 21. Report of executors for sale, H. Hooglandt, 1772; 3729 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- 22. Bond, Terhune and Schenck, 1735; 3730 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- 23. Deed, Stevensen to G.E. Stoothoff, 1702; 3731 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- 24. Commission as Justice of Peace, Governor Andros to E. Elbertsen, 1675; 3733 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- 25. Inventory of personal estate, W. Stoothoff, 1783; 3734 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- 26. Contract to sell, Innes to Lane, 1709; 3735 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- 27. Deed, G. Stoothoff to H. Roelofsen, 1709; 3736 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- 28. Articles of agreement, R. Schermerhorne, et. al. and heirs of E. Elbertsen, 1705; 3737 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- 29. Receipts of legacy, W. Gerretsem and I. Hegeman to E. Elbertsen's executors, 1695; 3738 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- 30. Petition, Town of Gravesend vs. E. Elbertsen, 1681; 3739 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- 31. Will, E. Elbertsen, circa 1700; 3740 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- 32. Will, G. Stoothoff, 1728; 3741 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- 33. Will. G. Stoothoff, 1722; 3742 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- 34. Will, W. Stoothoff, 1781; 3743 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- 35. Extract of will, E. Elbertsen, circa 1750; 3744 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- 36. Will, E. Elbertsen, 1760; 3745 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- 37. List of articles, G. Stoothoff, circa 1700; 3746 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- 38. Account, De Kay to E. Elbertsen, 1688; 3747 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- 39. Correspondence, G. Loockermans to E. Elbertsen, 1665; 3748 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- 40. Correspondence, Ruyven to E. Elbertsen, 1665; 3749 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- 41. Quit-claim, Schenck to J. Nevius, et. al., 1741; 3750 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- 42. Deed, P. Van der Beeck, et. al., 1699-1700; 3751 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- 43. Correspondence, D. Nevius to W. Stoothoff, 1751; 3752 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- 44. Correspondence, C. Hoogland to W. Stoothoff, 1772; 3753 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- 45. Correspondence, C. Stoothoff to W. Stoothoff, circa 1700; 3754 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- 46. Bond, W. Stoothoff to J.W. Wyckoff, 1753; 3756 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- 47. Bond, W. Stoothoff to H. Lott, 1742; 3757 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- 48. Bond, A. and W. Stoothoff to W. Stoothoff, 1764; 3758 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- 49. Bond, W. Stoothoff to Flatlands Dutch Church, 1736; 3759 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- 50. Bond, W. Stoothoff to J. Lott, 1744; 3760 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- 51. Bond, W. Stoothoff to C. Stoothoff, 1764; 3761 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- 52. Bond, W. Stoothoff to A. Coerten, 1745; 3762 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- 53. Bond, W. Stoothoff to C. Nevius, 1749; 3763 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- 54. Bond, W. Stoothoff to S. Boerum, 1756; 3764 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- 55. Bond, W. Stoothoff to J. Rapelyie, 1755; 3765 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- 56. Bond, W. Stoothoff to G. Stoothoff, 1764; 3766 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- 57. Bond, W. Stoothoff to G. Stoothoff, 1764; 3767 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- 58. Bond, W. Stoothoff to J. Amerman, 1744; 3768 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- 59. Bill of sale of "negro," W. Stoothoff to B. Lefferts, 1763; 3769 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- 60. Bond, W. Stoothoff to A. Voorhees, 1743; 3770 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- 61. Bond, W. Stoothoff to J. Neveyus, 1750; 3771 (Box 2, Folder 61)
- 62. Bond, W. Stoothoff to Flatlands Dutch Church, 1746; 3772 (Box 2, Folder 62)
- 63. Bond, W. Stoothoff to J. Vanderbilt, 1764; 3773 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- 64. Bond, W. Stoothoff to C. Stoothoff, 1749; 3774 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- 65. Bond, W. Stoothoff to J.W. Wyckoff, 1752; 3776 (Box 2, Folder 65)
- 66. Bond, W. Stoothoff to C. Stoothoff, 1741; 3777 (Box 2, Folder 66)
- 67. Bond, W. Stoothoff to J. Neveyus, 1750; 3778 (Box 2, Folder 67)
- 68. Bond, W. Stoothoff to J. Neveyus, 1750; 3779 (Box 2, Folder 68)
- 69. Bond, W. Stoothoff to W. Stoothoff, Jr., 1753; 3780 (Box 2, Folder 69)
- 70. Bond, W. Stoothoff to C. Nevius, 1749; 3781 (Box 2, Folder 70)
- 71. Deed, W. Stoothoof to C. Nevius, 1741; 3782 (Box 2, Folder 71)
- 72. Bond, W. Stoothoff to T. Elsworth, 1730; 3783 (Box 2, Folder 72)
- 73. Bond, J.W. Stoothoff to M. Stoothoff, 1792; 3784 (Box 2, Folder 73)
- 74. Bond, W. Stoothoff to J. Neveyus, 1750; 3785 (Box 2, Folder 74)
- 75. Bond, W. Stoothoff to E. and C. Stoothoff, 1739; 3789 (Box 2, Folder 75)
- 76. Correspondence, A. Kirkpatrick to J. Stoothoff, 1794; 3790 (Box 2, Folder 76)
- 77. Correspondence, A. Kirkpatrick to J. and W. Stoothoff, 1796; 3791 (Box 2, Folder 77)
- 78. Correspondence, D. Nevius to W. Stoothoff, 1749; 3792 (Box 2, Folder 78)
- 79. Correspondence, D. Nevius to W. Stoothoff, 1749; 3793 (Box 2, Folder 79)
- 80. Correspondence, J. Murray to H. Stoothoff, 1761; 3794 (Box 2, Folder 80)
- 80. Correspondence, H. Lott to W. Stoothoff, 1742; 3795 (Box 2, Folder 80)
- 81. Correspondence, C. Stoothoff to W. Stoothoff, 1757; 3796 (Box 2, Folder 81)
- 82. Affidavit, C. Stoothoff, 1764; 3797 (Box 2, Folder 82)
- 82. Receipt, C. Stoothoff to J. Cortelyou, 1731; 3798 (Box 2, Folder 82)
- 83. Correspondence, C. Stoothoff to W. Stoothoff, 1756; 3799 (Box 2, Folder 83)
- 84. Correspondence, C. Stoothoff to W. Stoothoff, 1762; 3800 (Box 2, Folder 84)
- 85. Correspondence, W. Smith, Jr. to W. Stoothoff, 1765; 3801 (Box 2, Folder 85)
- 85. Note, P. Amerman, circa 1750; 3802 (Box 2, Folder 85)
- 86. Correspondence, M. Wurts to W. Stoothoff, 1782; 3803 (Box 2, Folder 86)
- 86. Correspondence, W. Oake to W. Stoothoff, circa 1780; 3804 (Box 2, Folder 86)
- 87. Correspondence, W. Smith, Jr. to W. Stoothoff (2 letters), 1765, 1773; 3805 (Box 2, Folder 87)
- 88. Correspondence, A. Kirkpatrick to J. Stoothoff, 1794; 3806 (Box 2, Folder 88)
- 89. Correspondence, C. Stoothoff to W. Stoothoff, 1760; 3807 (Box 2, Folder 89)
- 90. Correspondence, M. Wurts to W. Stoothoff, 1782; 3808 (Box 2, Folder 90)
- 90. Bill, P.J. Marius to E. Elbertsen, 1687; 3809 (Box 2, Folder 90)
- 91. Birthdays of children, J. Stoothoff and C. Bogert, circa 1750; 3810 (Box 2, Folder 91)
- 92. Birthdays of children, W. Stoothoff and A. Van Voorhees, circa 1750; 3811 (Box 2, Folder 92)
- 93. Receipt of legacy, P. and I. Nevius to E. Elbertsen's executors, 1695; 3812 (Box 2, Folder 93)
- 93. Receipt of legacy, J. Albertse to E. Elbertsen's executors, 1695; 3813 (Box 2, Folder 93)
- 94. Correspondence, E. Stoothoff to G. Stoothoff, 1726; 3814 (Box 2, Folder 94)
- 94. Receipt, J. Kip to Town of Amersfoort, 1661; 3815 (Box 2, Folder 94)
- 95. Bill, W. Stoothoff, 1731-1732; 3816 (Box 2, Folder 95)
- 95. Bill, W. Stoothoff, 1735; 3817 (Box 2, Folder 95)
- 96. Correspondence, J. Hubbard to Captain Elbertsen, 1682; 3818 (Box 2, Folder 96)
- 96. Receipt, J.G. Van Couwenhoven to E. Elbertsen, 1683; 3819 (Box 2, Folder 96)
- 97. Bill, unidentified, circa 1700; 3820 (Box 2, Folder 97)
- 98. Agreement and receipt for legacies, G.W. Van Couwenhoven and E. Elbertsen, 1646; 3821 (Box 2, Folder 98)
- 99. Bill, F. Van Sycklen to G. and E. Elbertsen, circa 1700; 3822 (Box 2, Folder 99)
- 100. Debt, W. Stoothoff's heirs, circa 1750; 3823 (Box 2, Folder 100)
- 101. Account, T. Greedy, et. al., circa 1750; 3824 (Box 2, Folder 101)
- 101. Bill, W. Stoothoff to S. Williamsen, 1764-1773; 3825 (Box 2, Folder 101)
- 102. Account, unidentified, circa 1700; 3826 (Box 2, Folder 102)
- 102. Account, P. Cortlandt to G. Stoothoff, circa 1750; 3827 (Box 2, Folder 102)
- 102. Account, J. Turner to W. Stoothoff, 1773; 3828 (Box 2, Folder 102)
- 103. Affidavit, C. Van Elslandt, circa 1750; 3829 (Box 2, Folder 103)
- 103. Receipt, D. Lott to W. Stoothoff, 1780; 3830 (Box 2, Folder 103)
- 104. Receipt, P. Rutgers to W. Stoothoff, 1735; 3831 (Box 2, Folder 104)
- 104. Receipt, H. Remsen to W. Stoothoff, 1756; 3832 (Box 2, Folder 104)
- 104. Receipt, J. Lott to P. Stoothoff, circa 1750; 3833 (Box 2, Folder 104)
- 105. Receipt, W. Hanney to W. Stoothoff, 1762; 3834 (Box 2, Folder 105)
- 105. General Release, J. Van Bueren to W. Stoothoff, 1735-1736; 3835 (Box 2, Folder 105)
- 105. Receipt, C. Stoothoff to W. Stoothoff, 1765; 3836 (Box 2, Folder 105)
- 106. Receipt, T. Bergen to W. Stoothoff, 1781; 3837 (Box 2, Folder 106)
- 106. Receipt, J. Van Nuys to P. Stoothoff, 1788; 3838 (Box 2, Folder 106)
- 106. Receipt, S. Sprung to P. Stoothoff, 1785; 3839 (Box 2, Folder 106)
- 107. Receipt, J. Lott to P. Stoothoff, 1791; 3840 (Box 2, Folder 107)
- 107. Receipt, J. Lott to P. Stoothoff, 1789; 3841 (Box 2, Folder 107)
- 107. Receipt, S. Sprung to P. Stoothoff, 1787; 3842 (Box 2, Folder 107)
- 108. Bill, M. Schuyler, circa 1750; 3843 (Box 2, Folder 108)
- 108. Receipt, P. Wyckoff to P. Stoothoff, 1785; 3844 (Box 2, Folder 108)
- 109. List, heirs of G. Stoothoff, circa 1750; 3845 (Box 2, Folder 109)
- 109. Correspondence, H. Slecht to E. Elbertsen, circa 1700; 3846 (Box 2, Folder 109)
- 110. Account, report of Church Deacons, 1748; 3847 (Box 2, Folder 110)
- 111. Account, circa 1676-1682; 3848 (Box 2, Folder 111)
- 112. Account, 1676-1682; 3849 (Box 2, Folder 112)
- 113. Report of sale, W. Stoothoff, 1783-1796; 3850 (Box 2, Folder 113)
- 114. Account Book, E. Elbertsen, 1676-1682; 3856 (Box 2, Folder 114)
- 115. Account Book, E. Elbertsen, 1690-1714; 3857 (Box 2, Folder 115)
- 116. Indenture, J. Wickoff, et. al., 1703; 3858 (Box 2, Folder 116)
- Deed, John R. and Magaret Duryea to William Stoothoff, 1812; 22253 (Oversize OS-30)
  Property located in New Lots, Town of Flatbush.
- Deed, Jacob Ryersen to William W. Stoothoff, 1826; 22254 (Oversize OS-30)